{
  "title": "General_Aptitude-_CSE - Verbal_Ability_–_CSE — Slot 3 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Verbal_Ability_–_CSE — Slot 3",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following sentences:\n<br><br>\ni.   Everybody in the class is prepared for the exam.\n<br>ii.  Babu invited Danish to his home because he enjoys playing chess.<br><br>\nWhich of the following is the CORRECT observation about the above two sentences? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>(i) is grammatically correct and (ii) is unambiguous</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>(i) is grammatically incorrect and (ii) is unambiguous</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>(i) is grammatically correct and (ii) is ambiguous</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>(i) is grammatically incorrect and (ii) is ambiguous</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>(i) is grammatically correct and (ii) is ambiguous</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357474/gate-cse-2021-set-1-ga-question-3#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Goods and Services Tax (GST) is an indirect tax introduced in India in 2017 that is imposed on the supply of goods and services, and it subsumes all indirect taxes except few. It is a destination-based tax imposed on goods and services used, and it is not imposed at the point of origin from where goods come. GST also has a few components specific to state governments, central government  and Union Territories (UTs).<br><br>Which one of the following statements can be inferred from the given passage? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>GST is imposed on the production of goods and services.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>GST includes all indirect taxes.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>GST does not have a component specific to UT.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>GST is imposed at the point of usage of goods and services.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>GST is imposed at the point of usage of goods and services.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333235/gate-cse-2020-question-ga-6#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>The dawn of the 21st century witnessed the melting glaciers oscillating between giving too much and too little to billions of people who depend on them for fresh water. The UN climate report estimates that without deep cuts to man-made emissions, at least 30% of the northern hemisphere's surface permafrost could melt by the end of the century. Given this situation of imminent global exodus of billions of people displaced by rising seas, nation-states need to rethink their carbon footprint for political concerns, if not for environmental ones.<br><br>Which one of the following statements can be inferred from the given passage? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Nation-states do not have environmental concerns.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Nation-states are responsible for providing fresh water to billions of people.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Billions of people are responsible foe man-made emissions.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Billions of people are affected by melting glaciers.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Billions of people are affected by melting glaciers.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333237/gate-cse-2020-question-ga-4#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Select the word that fits the analogy:\n<br><br>\nCook : Cook :: Fly : _______ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Flyer</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Flying</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Flew</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Flighter</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Flyer</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333238/gate-cse-2020-question-ga-3#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>His knowledge of the subject was excellent but his classroom performance was_______. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>extremely poor</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>good</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>desirable</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>praiseworthy</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>extremely poor</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333239/gate-cse-2020-question-ga-2#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Raman is confident of speaking English _______six months as he has been practising regularly_______the last three weeks. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>during, for</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>for, since</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>for, in</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>within, for</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>within, for</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333240/gate-cse-2020-question-ga-1#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>\"A recent High Court judgement has sought to dispel the idea of begging as a disease - which leads to its stigmatization and criminalization  - and to regard it as a symptom. The underlying disease is the failure of the state to protect citizens who fall through the social security net.\"<br><br>\nWhich one of the following statements can be inferred from the given passage? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Beggars are lazy people who beg because they are unwilling to work</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Beggars are created because of the lack of social welfare schemes</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Begging is an offence that has to be dealt with firmly</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Begging has to be banned because it adversely affects the welfare of the state</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Beggars are created because of the lack of social welfare schemes</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302865/gate-cse-2019-question-ga-8#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>A court is to a judge as _________ is to a teacher. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>a student</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>a punishment</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>a syllabus</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>a school</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>a school</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302868/gate-cse-2019-question-ga-5#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>The search engine's business model ____ around the fulcrum of trust. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>revolves</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>plays</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>sinks</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>bursts</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>revolves</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302871/gate-cse-2019-question-ga-2#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>The expenditure on the project __________ as follows: equipment Rs.20 lakhs, salaries Rs.12 lakhs, and contingency Rs.3 lakhs. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>break down</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>break</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>breaks down</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>breaks</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>breaks down</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302872/gate-cse-2019-question-ga-1#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>A ________ investigation can sometimes yield new facts, but typically organized ones are more successful.\n<br><br>\nThe word that best fills the blank in the above sentence is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>meandering</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>timely</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>consistent</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>systematic</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>meandering</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/204063/gate-cse-2018-question-ga-2#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>\"From where are they bringing their books? _______ bringing _______ books from ________\"\n<br><br>\nThe words that best fill the blanks in the above sentence are <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Their, they're, there</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>They're, their, there</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>There, their, they're</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>They're, there,there</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>They're, their, there</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/204062/gate-cse-2018-question-ga-1#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>\"We lived in a culture that denied any merit to literary works, considering them important only when they were handmaidens to something seemingly more urgent - namely ideology. This was a country where all gestures, even the most private, were interpreted in political terms.\"<br><br>The author's belief that ideology is not as important as literature is revealed by the word: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>culture'</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>seemingly'</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>urgent'</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>political'</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>seemingly'</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118420/gate-cse-2017-set-2-question-ga-6#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Saturn is ___________ to be seen on a clear night with the naked eye. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>enough bright</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>bright enough</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>as enough bright</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>bright as enough</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>bright enough</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118416/gate-cse-2017-set-2-question-ga-2#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Choose the option with words that are not synonyms. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>aversion, dislike</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>luminous, radiant</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>plunder, loot</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>yielding, resistant</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>yielding, resistant</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118415/gate-cse-2017-set-2-question-ga-1#a_list\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}